### Matt Welsh

mdw@mdw.la https://www.mdw.la +1617-819-4504

### **Professional Summary**

I am a computer scientist and technology leader with 20 years of experience as an engineering director, software engineer, and professor. I have a strong research background in distributed systems, networks, mobile computing, and embedded systems. I have designed and implemented large systems supporting more than a billion users, deployed wireless sensors on active volcanoes, and published more than 70 scientific papers. I enjoy working on the bleeding edge of technology and developing products to improve the lives of users all over the world.

### **Experience**

Principal Engineer Xnor.ai Seattle, WA March 2019 - present

I am head of the Platform and Systems teams at Xnor.ai, a Seattle-based startup that is developing fast, power-efficient AI capabilities for edge devices, such as low-power CPUs. Xnor's technology makes it possible to run, for example, 30 fps real-time object and person detection and tracking on an embedded device such as a Raspberry Pi. I am both an individual contributor, writing a substantial amount of code, as well as a manager of two teams comprising 12 engineers. Our projects include:

- Xnor's CPU-efficient inference engine, which compresses and optimizes ML models to run on low-power devices.
- Xnor's Al2GO platform (<a href="https://ai2go.xnor.ai">https://ai2go.xnor.ai</a>), a free SDK making it possible to embed fast Al models with just a few lines of code.
- Xnor's infrastructure for model training, testing, benchmarking, continuous integration, and code health.
- Specialized capabilities and integration support for Xnor's largest customer engagements.

Principal Engineer Google, Inc.

Seattle, WA June 2010 - March 2019

I led the Chrome Mobile team in Seattle and Kirkland, with a focus on optimizing the web experience for users in emerging markets such as India, Indonesia, and sub-Saharan Africa. I started the team and grew it to more than 40 engineers. As a result of our team's work, grew Chrome to more than a billion users in emerging markets. Our work spanned server-side and client-side technologies. Some of my team's projects include:

- Flywheel, a proxy service for compressing mobile web pages, in use by more than 650M users of Chrome, driving tens of billions of queries per day.
- Client-side optimizations to simplify page loading and rendering, using server hinting to tailor the optimizations for individual web pages.
- Adding capabilities to Chrome to enable downloading and prefetching of web content to enable users with intermittent connectivity to browse while offline.
- New browser features to help users discover new web content and more effectively multitask on small screens.

# Professor of Computer Science Harvard University

Cambridge, MA July 2003 - July 2011

Led a research team of more than a dozen graduate students, postdocs, undergrads, and research staff focused on exploring the technology ramifications of tiny, embedded wireless sensors, with applications such as geological monitoring and healthcare.

- We developed new operating systems, network protocols, and programming models for networks of embedded, 8-bit microcontrollers with low-power radios.
- We evaluated our work through deep engagements with domain scientists, deploying sensor networks on two active volcanoes in Ecuador, on street lights throughout the city of Cambridge, and in lab tests for patients being treated for Parkinson's Disease.
- Taught undergraduate and graduate courses on Operating Systems, Computer Architecture, Distributed Systems, and Wireless Networking.
- Awarded tenure and promoted to full professor in 2010.

## Senior Researcher Intel Research

Berkeley, CA August 2002 - July 2003

Following my PhD work at Berkeley, I spent a year at Intel Research, developing a new programming language and compiler chain for embedded wireless sensors, called NesC. This work was published in PLDI 2003, won the "most influential paper" award 10 years later, and has been cited more than 2500 times.

### Skills

- I am an expert in operating systems, networks, wireless, mobile computing, and distributed systems, and have published and served on program committees for conferences in these areas.
- Long track record of driving successful technology projects, ranging from academic research efforts to multi-team projects supporting more than a billion users.
- Strong technical background in software development, fluent in Go, C++, C, Java, Python, and SQL, with extensive experience developing for Linux, Android, and mobile web platforms.
- Seasoned organizational leader with experience building, scaling, and reorganizing teams; mentoring and career development; managing performance and balancing engineering investments.
- Strong communication skills as an author of many scientific articles and books, as well as experience as a teacher, technical speaker, and mentor.
- I am passionate about leveraging technology to address humanitarian needs and improve the lives of people.

### Education

Ph.D., Computer Science

UC Berkeley, December 2002

Thesis title: An Architecture for Highly Concurrent, Well-Conditioned Internet Services

Masters of Science, Computer Science
Bachelor of Science, Computer Science

UC Berkeley, December 1999 Cornell University, May 1996

Full academic CV with publication list is available at <a href="https://www.mdw.la/mattwelsh-cv.pdf">https://www.mdw.la/mattwelsh-cv.pdf</a>